[SPEAKER_00]: How do I practice compassion towards my fellow beings according to the Buddha's teaching?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha didn't teach compassion in a way of simply just being affected by the fact that somebody else suffers, like being kind of moved by
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a natural state.
[SPEAKER_01]: What the Buddha mentioned has or advised people to cultivate was, well, first of all, metta, which was absence of your will or friendliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have metta, which is friendliness, karuṇa, which is compassion, mudita, which is appreciation, and upeka, which is equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all of the four,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the difference between that and the compassion that people usually talk about, is that the second one is biased.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you know, for instance, you have a feeling of affinity towards somebody, you want to help them, and in the process, you're more often than not willing to compromise the interests of somebody else or something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for instance, you're, whatever it might be, a family member, loved one, pet,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it is, you would, for example, be willing to harm somebody in order to protect them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's by abandoning that, that you would... Because, see, the problem isn't that you don't have compassion towards anybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you don't have compassion universally.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, there are some cases where you are biased because of your attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you have to look into is not like, how do I choose what people I can be compassionate with, because anybody you choose is almost certainly already going to be precisely somebody who you don't need to develop compassion for.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to look at the worst-case scenario and imagine the things that would actively incline your mind towards hatred, and essentially develop a mind where you know that
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how unpleasant it becomes, you will not start making those... you will not start acting out of those biases, so that even if the people who are most significant to you are literally going to die, you would still not delight in the suffering of whoever is going to kill them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not a thing that you would do by
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whenever you think about individual people, and it's a principle in mathematics as well, you can't reach infinity by adding individual parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only... like, infinity can only be covered by encompassing the nature of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the nature of the thing that makes you not have compassion is discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it feels unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: In certain situations, whoever or whatever is responsible for that discomfort, is excluded from your compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that exclusion is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the lack of an inclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you see that in the natural state, when you don't have any reason to hate someone, you're automatically interested in their welfare.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because you haven't chased after each individual person and included them in the compassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of that discomfort that you're not trained in regard to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't sufficiently taught yourself to not take discomfort as an excuse for hatred or for animosity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, could one say as well, if one includes oneself in that compassion... Well, you don't need to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you don't exclude yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would actually realize that compassion towards yourself would be developing yourself in regards to that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, the thing is, like, at the end of the day, you are already moved by your own feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, that's the one compassion that you will not be able to not have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're basically saying, it is about your own feelings, but that is always the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, whenever you would be kind of engaged in protecting somebody, or hating somebody, or whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what poetic ideas you hold.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be because of how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you have to simply accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, there's no avenue for development.
[SPEAKER_01]: To realize that, like, all of these things I'm doing, whether it's
[SPEAKER_01]: hating or trying to abandon hatred is going to be because of how I feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, through that avenue, you can start to see, okay, so all of this reactions down the line of hating, not being compassionate, which is like a
[SPEAKER_01]: A less coarse form of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that comes first from the unwillingness to just leave the discomfort be what it is and not have to defend yourself against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, actually, it doesn't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not that, you know, when you kill someone out of revenge,
[SPEAKER_01]: That it actually undoes whatever bad thing was happening that made you suffer to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just makes you kind of feel satisfied that you did something about it, but that's completely separate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it actually is pointless that when displeasure is occurring, that you try to defend yourself implicitly against it by blaming it on somebody and
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, that is the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: The action is the exclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You exclude the person out of the basis of friendliness or the basis of compassion, out of that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, if you simply saw or dwelt on that lack of need for that action, for that exclusion, you saw how it makes no difference and it actually makes the problem worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you could see, oh, I could actually have the discomfort there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I don't engage in all of these actions of resisting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, why would it be a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ironically, you're making it worse through the exclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, that is one of the forms that craving takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like reaction towards unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the whole point is, in those very, sort of, acutely
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of like... it feels very, very personal scenarios, where it's like the last time... or it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: You shouldn't exclude that person from your compassion, because, like, it's, you know, the worst imaginable thing they did to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you need to not try to cultivate these rosy thoughts, which is ultimately artificial.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you're holding that structure up, and it's going to fall as soon as you stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to do, which is actually a form of samādhi, which by definition has to be effortless,
[SPEAKER_01]: is to undo that impulse of excluding the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's a natural thing to not want somebody else to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only start wanting that as a coping mechanism in regard to your discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stop that coping mechanism by reflecting on its pointlessness, for instance,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, by abandoning that gratuitous sense of... gratuitous attitude of resistance and discomfort, you would know that you have included everyone automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only re... you would never conceivably hate someone or have any type of animosity towards someone.
[SPEAKER_01]: universally, you have abandoned your will through one thing, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through one gateway, you have included the entire world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is your resistance towards feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, each of the four Brahma-vihāras has its own opposite
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing you have to do to cultivate, for instance, metta, which is the first step, is see that ill-will is an activity that you do in order to try to shelter yourself from displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of adding this noise there, that supposedly, through some magical thinking, will make the displeasure not be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, actually, if I don't engage in this, it's actually less of a burden, both for myself and for everybody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you purify your mind from your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be clear that that principle, in its nature,
[SPEAKER_01]: is perilous, pointless, eh... does not benefit anybody, not even you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the only way you would abandon it in every possible instance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas the... what people usually do, which is force yourself to love someone, that has nothing to do with the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you, eh... let's say you were born... you were somebody who every single person you met in your life
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as long as you're alive and you have things that are pleasing to you and things that are displeasing to you, you will be capable of hatred.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just a matter of you not yet having met somebody who would upset you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, essentially, what... what... or some situation in which you would be upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what people are basically doing when they try this supposed metta practice, or loving-kindness, as it's called nowadays, is just putting yourself in that state where, like, circumstantially, I'm in a good mood towards everyone, but there's always going to be some unforeseen
[SPEAKER_01]: That you haven't accounted for, because that's the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's infinite, the range of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's going to disturb you now, when it comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's never going to be boundless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant when I said before, like, you can't reach infinity by adding individual parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that gateway is that action of resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have to recognize that's an action, a mental action that I engage with.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the unpleasant feeling presents itself, I decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as a super explicit choice, but it's something that I could not do.
[SPEAKER_01]: To explore and dwell on the details of these aversive perceptions of, like, you know, the negative qualities of somebody, for instance, and how much of a fool they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop yourself from doing that, when there is the pressure to do so, because of this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you abandon that activity in all its forms, what you will be left with is the more natural state where, you know, imagine you see somebody on the street for the first time and there's nobody... there's no reason for you to hate them, there's no reason for you to love them either, because you know nothing about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if that person... like, it would be inconceivable to, out of the blue, start wishing them harm.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you hadn't kind of thought about that person, it would not be a thought of harming them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you would be left with, in regard to the whole world, if you were to abandon that action of ill-will, which is what obstructs the more fundamental attitude of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it evolved, the whole thing evolves or culminates in an even more fundamental attitude of equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is not caring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a super refined form of care.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, like, when the people confuse the metta-sutta as, like, a mother protecting her own child.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should treat all beings...
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas the clear meaning is, that's how you would protect your own mind of metta, like a mother would protect her own child.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it's not about being involved with the welfare of other beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about being very vigilant, not to let your mind, not to let yourself engage in these pathways of resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the more you do that, the less involved with anyone you will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most refined and highest of the Brahmanic arts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a... what do you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: A certain state of non-care or care-freeness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, non-caring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, non-caring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which some people might associate with, like, callousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's an activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You intentionally decide to dismiss something you could have thought about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you... out of resistance to the effort or whatever, you decide not to think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equanimity is like, I actually don't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that I care to the extent of dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, the care does not arise in the first place.